<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Musarum deliciae Contayning more then a select century of royall Latine anagrams, besides diverse written in English, upon the sacred name and titles of our dread soveraigne and of his dearest consort, and their most princely progeny. Together with apposite anagrams upon all the English monarchs that have lived and died since the union of the royall roses and houses of Yorke and Lancaster. Some few of those extracted from his Maiesties imperiall name, have been heretofore presented to his royall hands with gracious acceptance. The Latine anagrammes are expressed in English verses in the opposite columne. Perused anew, and now published altogether, (with the authors assent) by Arthur Pyne Esquire, to whom the anagrams made in honour of the Prince his Highnesse were in speciall manner directed.</title>
            <author>Pyne, John, d. 1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110559</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 974:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Musarum deliciae Contayning more then a select century of royall Latine anagrams, besides diverse written in English, upon the sacred name and titles of our dread soveraigne and of his dearest consort, and their most princely progeny. Together with apposite anagrams upon all the English monarchs that have lived and died since the union of the royall roses and houses of Yorke and Lancaster. Some few of those extracted from his Maiesties imperiall name, have been heretofore presented to his royall hands with gracious acceptance. The Latine anagrammes are expressed in English verses in the opposite columne. Perused anew, and now published altogether, (with the authors assent) by Arthur Pyne Esquire, to whom the anagrams made in honour of the Prince his Highnesse were in speciall manner directed.</title>
                  <author>Pyne, John, d. 1644.</author>
                  <author>Pyne, Arthur.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Anne Griffin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Pyne.</note>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Arthur Pyne.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Royall anagrams expressed in English.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anagrams --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MVSARVM DELICIAE.</p>
            <p>CONTAYNING MORE then a ſelect Century of royall Latine Anagrams, beſides diverſe written in Engliſh, upon the ſacred name and titles of our Dread Soveraigne and of his deareſt Conſort, and their moſt Princely Progeny.</p>
            <p>Together with appoſite Anagrams upon all the Engliſh Monarchs that have lived and died ſince the union of the royall roſes and houſes of Yorke and Lancaſter.</p>
            <p>Some few of thoſe extracted from his Maieſties Imperiall Name, have been heretofore preſented to his Royall hands with gracious acceptance.</p>
            <p>The Latine Anagrammes are expreſſed in Engliſh verſes in the oppoſite Columne.</p>
            <p>Peruſed anew, and now publiſhed altogether, (with the Authors aſſent) by <hi>Arthur Pyne</hi> Eſquire, to whom the Anagrams made in honour of the Prince his Highneſſe were in ſpeciall manner directed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
               <p>Non contentio animi, ſed relaxatio.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> London printed by <hi>Anne Griffin.</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:2"/>
            <head>PRAEFATIO POETICA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Ad Carolum Regem Auguſtum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carole qui triplicis fulges diademate Regni,</l>
               <l>Ter populo dilecte, Deo dilecte ter-uni;</l>
               <l>(<note n="*" place="margin">Virgil.</note> Semper honos nomen<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tuum laudes<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manebunt;)</l>
               <l>Scripta tuam accipias in laudem, nomen, honorem.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Charles with three rich diadems high-crowned,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thrice lov'd of men, the Trinities delight;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For your great</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Like Gods peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, high in praiſe and in name, and in honour. <hi>Deut</hi> 26.19.</note> 
                  <hi>honour, name, and praiſe renowned:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In praiſe of your moſt honour'd name I write.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the Queenes Maieſty.</head>
            <l>Great Queene, great Britaines other greater light;</l>
            <l>My Muſe (although leaſt worthy) here brings forth</l>
            <l>Choice Anagrams (in which French wits delight)</l>
            <l>To teſtifie her ſervice, and your worth.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:3"/>
            <head>Ad Carolum Principem infantem.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Haeredum flos ſumme, haeres digniſſime<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſorum &amp; liliorum.</note> florum,</l>
               <l>Gallica quos tellus, quoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Britanna tulit;</l>
               <l>Ecce tibi, Princeps, Muſarum flosculus horti</l>
               <l>Ad Tamiſim à Tamarae margine miſſus adeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>You</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">He alludeth to the flowring moneth of May in which the Prince was borne.</note> 
                  <hi>flow'r of Princes whom French lillyes ſhield,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And the faire roſes of theſe Britiſh Realmes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accept ſome flow'rs of the Pierian field,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">The author li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth neere the bankes of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</note> 
                  <hi>Tamar brought to Thames the Prince of Streames.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the Duke of Yorke.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>Iames</hi> now is what <hi>Charles</hi> was in th'unions Spring,</l>
            <l>Yorkes duke deſcended from the royall race:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Charles</hi> is what <hi>Iames</hi> then was, the Soveraigne King</l>
            <l>Of all this Iſland, through Gods Soveraigne Grace.</l>
            <l>Sith th'heav'ns are pleas'd thus to tranſpoſe great names;</l>
            <l>Deigne your acceptance to theſe Anagrams.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the Lady Mary.</head>
            <l>Moſt princely Lady, ſome poeticke Layes,</l>
            <l>Preſuming on your leave, I here advance</l>
            <l>To you, who raiſed are to be the praiſe</l>
            <l>And ornament of Britaine and of France.</l>
            <l>My chaſte Muſe free's from feares of juſt offence,</l>
            <l>Clad (like your infant yeeres) in innocence.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:3"/>
            <head>The fourefold Anagram following compareth the Kings Maieſty for his princely literature to the Laurell, the crowne of learning; for his rare eminency and conſtant piety, to the Cedar, whoſe lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e never falleth, and whoſe fruit never faileth; for the gracious br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtneſſe of royall maieſty, to the morning inlightening and enlivening the earth; and for all perfections of grace and government, to that ſacred and learned king <hi>Alured,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Altred,</hi> whoſe valour and vertue are ſo highly extolled by our hiſtorians.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anagramma</hi> quadruplex.</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvarde.</l>
               <l>1. Tu laurûs es decôra,</l>
               <l>2. Tu ſola vera Cedrus:</l>
               <l>3. Sed luces vt Aurora,</l>
               <l>4. O ſacer vt Aluredus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like the faire laurell you appeare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You like the goodly Cedar ſpread:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But you ſhine at the morning cleere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A ſacred King like Alured.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>In the next Anagram his maieſty is moſt fitly likened to that gotlly and gracious king <hi>Oſwald,</hi> whoſe name (ſaith our Antiquary)'s equivalent in ſignification with <hi>Steward.</hi> This <hi>Oſwald</hi> having beene baptized among the Scots was afterward crowned King ouer the Engliſh, and (ſo <hi>Bede</hi> writeth) did cauſe this whole Iſland to flow with peace and flouriſh with plenty.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stewardus.</l>
               <l>Tercarus Oſwaldus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like deare Saint Oſwald whom hiſtorians found</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Scotland chriſtend and in England crown'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Other Anagrams acknowledging his ſacred Maieſty to be as the cleare light, and the deare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of his loyall people.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anagramma</hi> duplex.</head>
               <l>[Carolus Steuarde.]</l>
               <l>1. Dote rarus luceas;</l>
               <l>2. Sol acer et arduus,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enrich'd with heau'ns rare dower, continue ſhining;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like th'high plac'd Sun in power, not in declining.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus primus Steuardus totius Albionis Rex ſereniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Noſtra lux or ſuet uſu clariſſima, nos ſi deſeris tu, peribimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our light whoſe ray and riſing doth us cheriſh;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Should you away, we drown'd in teares muſt periſh.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The two following Anagrams, the latter of which is contryved into an exact hexameter and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tameter verſe, doe declare his majeſty to be the beauty and ſafety, the ornament and the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his dominions.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus Stevvardus Angliae et Scotiae Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Suorum decor, ac genti ſuae laeta ſalutis anchora.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>He under God his great Protectour, ſtand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As th'ornament and anchor of his Lands.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus primus Stevvardus, et Anglorum, et Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Rex ac Monarcha ſereniſſimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Arx ſuprema ſuis, ſummus decor, anchora grata,</l>
               <l>Cor, turris, columen, lumen et eſto ſuis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His peoples ſtay, their refuge, and ſafe fort,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their heart, their eye, their beauty, and ſupport.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:4"/>
            <p>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maieſties royall marriage with the Lady Mary Burbon was thus celebrated in Heroicall Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammaticall verſes, and in ſundry other Anagrams to them annexed.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus primus Angliae et Scotiae Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Carus amore cito, ac Gallis pius, enthea Norma.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His nuptiall loue was deare and undelayd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee to the French an heav'nly rule and ayd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus unitae Angliae et Scotine Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Sic volat alina, venit caſtae Regina coronae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The faireſt Queene came flying on loves wing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto the crowne of Charles the chaſteſt king.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius Rex.</l>
               <l>Creaturus Vxori Salutes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>He having taken her to wife, will make her</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of moſt aboundant happineſſe partaker.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus primus Stevvartius</l>
               <l>Angliae Rex potentiſſimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Erat (ſic Gallae notus, unitus)</l>
               <l>Pius ſemper Vxoris Maritus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus knowne and knit vnto his peereleſſe Queene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A pious Husband he hath ever beene.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius Angliae et Scotiae Monarcha.</l>
               <l>Sis Cato, Numa, Curlus,</l>
               <l>Ter carae Gallae vita et honos.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like Numa, Curius and Cato chaſte;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her life and honour whom his love embrac'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus I. Stevvartius Monarcha Britanniae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Conſtans Mariae turtur haberis, vnica viola.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Turtle deere that to his Peere</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>hath conſtant love expreſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The violet that heav'n did ſet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>for Maries faireſt breaſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus I. Stevvardus, et Britannorum</l>
               <l>Scotiaequè Monarcha optimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Vultu atquè motibus perdecotus,</l>
               <l>Nova norma ſancti et caſti amoris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe modeſt looke and life are rules to move</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our looſer times to learne a chaſter love.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus I. Stevvardus praecellentiſſimus</l>
               <l>et Rex et Monarcha Britannicus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Sic turſus virtus ipſa amorum excellens</l>
               <l>et alta viret, bina corda nectens.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee now behold (like thoſe of old)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>loves higheſt power to raigne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which in this faire and high borne paire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>hath made one heart of twaine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:4"/>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius vnitae Angliae ſimul</l>
               <l>ac Scotiae Monarcha ſereniſſimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Sunt Muſis aevo hoc natis verè aurea ſecla,</l>
               <l>Nam Regum caſtis lilia iuncta roſis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The golden age, as I preſage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall now the Muſes nouriſh;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sith with the Roſe the Lilly grow's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and being crown'd doth flouriſh.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus I. Steuartius vnitae Angliae Scotiaequè Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Lilio caſto iuueniquè natae</l>
               <l>Amantur Roſae, ſuccis gratae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The tender Lilly through loves chaſte device,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enioyes the pleaſant Roſes cordiall iuyce.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The heavenly protection extended towards his Maieſty through the whole courſe of his life is thus anagrammatically acknowledged.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus Steuartius et Rex et Monarcha Angliae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>— Te amavit</l>
               <l>(O terrâ laetans Rex!) chorus Angelicus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O king on earth triumphing! from above,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You, the triumphant Angels guard and love.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The late deplored condition of his Maieſties exiled onely Siſter was thus commiſerated in an Anagram.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Rex, Britonum Caeſar.</l>
               <l>Cur ſoror exul ſacra manebit?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Why ſhall his ſacred Siſter thus remain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An exile and expos'd to foes diſdaine?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The following Anagrams were compoſed in relation to his Maieſties moſt pious and vertuous en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowments, which make him parallel to the moſt famous Princes, and pretious to his loyall people.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuart.</l>
               <l>Clarus ſorte tuâ.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His lot befell him in the faireſt field.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartus.</l>
               <l>Solus ſacra tuetur.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee's under God, our Churches onely ſhield.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr. duplex</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartius.</l>
               <l>1. Vt cor ſalutare suis</l>
               <l>2. Ortu et ausis clarus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His loyall Subiects healthfull heart and mirth;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Renowned both for enterpriſe, and birth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stuartius eſt</l>
               <l>Carus et ut ros ſalutis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:5"/>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius Angliae</l>
               <l>et Scotiae Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Tuae et ara gentis ac oculus:</l>
               <l>Amor, oris ac anhelitus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His peoples refuge, love and ſweet delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Breath of their mouth, and of their eyes the light.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvardus.</l>
               <l>Ades vt rarus oculus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevartus Rex Britanniae.</l>
               <l>Virtute Rebus annexâ, ſtas clarior.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who ſtand's the more renown'd in mens opinions</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ioyning vertues great with large dominions.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartus Britannorum</l>
               <l>Monarcha ſerenissimus.</l>
               <l>Muſis en Conſtantinus rarus;</l>
               <l>Orbi almus, ter amore charus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Conſtantine unto the Chriſtian Muſes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fair'ſt and dear'ſt Prince that the world produces.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius</l>
               <l>Verus auctor ſalutis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whom all true-hearted Britons doe confeſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be th'Augmenter of their happineſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma duplex.</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartius.</l>
               <l>1. Tuta salus. vires, cor.</l>
               <l>2. Sicut roſa salvetur!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their ſafe health, and their ſtrength and heart is he.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O let him as the Roſe preſerved be!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus primus Stevvartus validissimè po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens vuitae Angliae et Scotiae Monarcha.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Carum adeò cor, vita, salus Anglis venit; Ipsi</l>
               <l>Mars venit, et Muſae, Clio, Arethuſa, potens.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>When he our ſo deare heart, life, health bècame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Breath of our noſtrils, glory of his name:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars and the Muſes with Diana's mate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Came to him to attend his royall State.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus primus Steuartus, Angliae Scotiae</l>
               <l>Hiberniacquè Monarcha ter honoratissimus, et munificentissimus; valdè acer ac mitus</l>
               <l>Veritatis et Fidei Defensor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>En fecit noſtris Is ſanè haec otia Musis:</l>
               <l>Verum Virtutis gloria calcar habet.</l>
               <l>Nam laudi eſt huic mitis amor, nequè forma fereno</l>
               <l>Ipsi, nec virtus rara, fidesvè deeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Loe thus the glory that our king hath won,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gave ſpurre to my dull verſe, and made it run.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For, gentleneſſe, faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, vertues rare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crowne Charles the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Titles given by hiſtorians to the royall name of Charles.</note> 
                  <hi>wiſe, the welbelou'd, the faire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>A twofold Anagram.</head>
               <l>Charles Steuart.</l>
               <l>1. Cal's true hearts.</l>
               <l>2. Hate's cruel arts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercy and Truth have met in him as Mates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He cal's true hearts, and cruel arts he hate's.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:5"/>
            <head>The Queenes Maieſty is compared in the ſix fold Anagram following to the Turtle for her conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall chaſtity and fidelity; to the Aſian myrrhe and Phaenix for her incorrupt ſincerity, and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar excellency, and concluded to be a moſt gentle and gracious Lady.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma hexaſticon.</head>
               <l>[Maria Stevvartia.]</l>
               <l>1. Ea turturi amaſia,</l>
               <l>2. Marita, vera, iuſta.</l>
               <l>3. Vt avis etiam rara.</l>
               <l>4. Aut ut Aſiae mirrha.</l>
               <l>5. Viris amata vt hera</l>
               <l>6. Mitis, aurata, vera.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee's mate vnto a Turtle faire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A faithfull wife and ever true.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee's of her ſexe the Phenix rare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And like Myrrhe which in Aſia grew.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Lady, of all men belov'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſt gentle, excellent, approv'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The royall aboundance of the Queenes vertues, and her earneſt deſire to bynde the Britiſh and French ſcepters in an everlaſting league, together with our devout prayers that ſhee may flouriſh like the pleaſant Vine in her royall branches, and long liue with her Lord, the King, have occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this fourefold Anagram,</p>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anagramma</hi> quadruplex.</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvartia Regina.</l>
               <l>1. Ara virtutis regia, amaena;</l>
               <l>2. Vis maritare regna avita.</l>
               <l>3. Ramis vireat grata vinea,</l>
               <l>4. Vna ſit vera, regia Marita.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertues faire Altar, richly furniſhed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You royally will ancient kingdomes wed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O let this pleaſant Vine her branches ſpread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And never deck a</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <l>—coniuge gaudeat uno,</l>
                     <l>Et ſemper natis gaudeat illa tribus.</l>
                     <bibl>Martial.. epig. 54. lib. 11.</bibl>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſecond husbands bed!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Vpon her Maieſties admired vertues, mildneſſe, beauty, royall deſcent; happy marriage, peace-loving diſpoſition, rare perfection and excellent ſharpeneſſe and ripeneſſe of wit and judgement, theſe Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams have beene written.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Maria Steuarta Regina.</l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n' Aſtraea mira, regia?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A iuſt Aſtraea you have ever beene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuſtly admired, and moſt royall Queene.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr. duplex.</head>
               <l>Maria Stuartia Regina.</l>
               <l>1. Avê Martis atri ignara;</l>
               <l>2. Mitis, niuea, grata, rara.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haile Lady taking no delight in war,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſt calme and comely, gracious and rare.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anagramma</hi> duplex.</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvarta Regina.</l>
               <l>1. Avê nimis arguta et rara;</l>
               <l>2. Grata tuis Minervae ara.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haile worthieſt Queene in wit excelling far,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You to your traine Minerva's Altar are.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Maria Stevvartia Anglorum Regina.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>—natu</l>
               <l>Tu re regalis, magna (Maria) Viro.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Borne of a royal houſe, and growne</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">like <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſſe who was alſo the daughter of an Henry, of whom we reade <hi>Magna ortu, maier<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Viro—</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>great ſince,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By being the Spouſe of ſo renoun'd a Prince.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:6"/>
               <l>Maria Stevvartia Anglorum Regina.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Regali or natu ſum margarita nivea.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>For royall ornaments deſerving praiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As the white orient pearle of theſe our dayes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Maria Stevvard vnitae et Angliae ac Scotorum Regina.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>—Advenit (ô) ſic</l>
               <l>Alma Ceres, et Iuno grata, arguta Minerva!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fruitfull as Ceres, for a gracefull gate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">—incedens Iuno, Minerva loquens. Ang.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuno, for ſharpe wit Minerva's mate.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Maria Steuard.</l>
               <l>Marti adverſa.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvart.</l>
               <l>Tu Martia versa.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your ſelfe you ſhew (through all your life)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be a Foe to warre, and ſtrife.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Steuarta.</l>
               <l>Atas tueti amat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your love to peace that lovely mak's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Staye's crownes and altars which warre ſhake's.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvart.</l>
               <l>Maturitas vera.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>You in true ripeneſſe of perfection ſhine,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvarta.</l>
               <l>Aurea maturitas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like perfit gold dig'd from the pureſt Mine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Of the Queenes thriſe amiable countenance and admirable carriage winning affections at firſt view, theſe Anagrams have beene written.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvart.</l>
               <l>Visa ter amatur.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>This gracious Queene of all approv'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where ſhee's once ſeene, is thrice belov'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Steuarda Regina.</l>
               <l>Tu hera digna eras amati.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Lady meerely for great worth affected,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Belov'd ſincerely, worthily reſpected.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Maria Steuarda Regina Anglica.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Amati digna es vt rara, Angelica.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Love's precious Iemme, the deare delight of all;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beauties bright beame, rare, faire, Angelicall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagram.</head>
               <l>Mary Steward.</l>
               <l>Draw's my heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O how attractive are her vertuous parts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The load-ſtone and the load-ſtarre of mens hearts.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:6"/>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Marie Steuard.</l>
               <l>Veſta married.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee's chaſte as Veſta, and vpon fames wing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mounts higher, marryed to the chaſteſt king.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The great Bleſſings which Great Britaine hopeth to enioy in her young Prince Charles have beene anagrammatically expreſſed as followeth.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius haeres Britannicus.</l>
               <l>Tun' ut alba viris roſa ſua viter crescens?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like to the faire white roſe you doe ariſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which ſo, delightfull growe's to all men's eyes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr. duplex.</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius.</l>
               <l>1. Vir eſto lautus, catus.</l>
               <l>2. Coelitùs satur arvus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grow fayre and deare by grace and nature dreſſed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And like a field with heav'nly fulneſſe bleſſed.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartus regiminis haeres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Cum veſtris iunge laurea ſerta rosis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still with your royall engliſh roſes ioyne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Laurell garland of the Arts divine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartius haeres.</l>
               <l>Arte charus sis et aureolus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grow deare through learned arts (while wars wax cruell)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bee in this iron age a golden Iewell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius.</l>
               <l>Cultus ut roſa vireas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grow faire and flouriſh, and freſh odours yeeld,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartus.</l>
               <l>Vt roſa cultus eras.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deck'd like the roſe that doth adorne the field.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stuartius haeres.</l>
               <l>Iuſtus heros arte clarus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſt nobly iuſt, and for ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h art renown'd,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carelus Stevvartus Princeps Angliac.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Is aptè ornatus, clarus, Angelicus puer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>From heaven fitly furniſh'd to be crown'd,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuardus Walliae Princeps.</l>
               <l>Ille novus, purus, ac reparatus Alcides</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>In whom Alcides is reſtor'd a new,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strengthned with vertue, vices to ſubdue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:7"/>
            <p>In the following Anagrams the Prince as the hopefull heyre of his royall Fathers reſplendent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, is compared to thoſe glorious heavenly bodies the Sunne and Starres, and to thoſe renowned Princes of Britaine King Arthur and King Lucius, of whom the former hath his name deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from that northerne fixed ſtarre Arcturus, and the latter from the light which the Sunne ſhed's upon the earth, &amp;c.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartius haeres Britannicus.</l>
               <l>Essicut Arthurus ac verè Sol Britannis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yare like Prince Arthur in our Britiſh Story,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And like the Sun riſing in perfit glory.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartus.</l>
               <l>Tu Sol es, ac Arthurus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius Inſulae Britannicae Princeps.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Ortus an is iuuenis praeclarus páce Britannis</l>
               <l>Lucet?—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shining from th'youthfull Spring with radiant rayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon the Britons in faire peacefull dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Carolus Princeps Stuartius Borboniusquè, et proles Britannica.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>—Sol perbonus, atque Britannis</l>
               <l>Ac orbi Princeps Lucius ortus erat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>In you both we and all the world have won</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Another</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lucius Rex, agnomine magni ſplendoris. Nennius.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucius, yea another Sun.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvardus Princeps Britanniae.</l>
               <l>Tu rarus orbi Natus, principale ſanè decus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A rare ſonne borne vnto the world, and ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be its honour and chiefe ornament.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Carolus Stevvartius.</l>
               <l>Tu carus ut ſol äerius.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deare as the Sun which from the heav'n doth ſhine;</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagranma</head>
               <l>Carolus Steuartus.</l>
               <l>Orſu ut aſtra luces.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cleare as the Starrs, and every way divine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>To Charles Steuart.</l>
               <l>Thou cleareſt Star.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Charles Stevvard.</l>
               <l>Such a dear luſtre!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou cleareſt Starre now riſing in the North,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The load-ſtar of the Chriſtian Worlds affection:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spreading bright beames of rareſt Princely worth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stand fix't, and give to Sea and land direction.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shining in graces and in vertues here,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such a deare luſtre to the Britons give,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Till thou reach heav'n like to a Starre moſt cleere)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That in that light they may ſee how to live,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:7"/>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Vnto Charles Stevvart.</l>
               <l>No Turtle was chaſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Charles Steuart.</l>
               <l>As the chaſt Ruler.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee's fit to rule, then whom no Turtle's chaſter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whom chaſtity it ſelfe ſhall rule and maſter.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Charles Stuart.</l>
               <l>A Rachels truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Royall Rachel link't with Iacobs heire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Long truſted for a princely propagation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till God fulfill'd unto that happy Paire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Both Rachels truſt, and their realmes expectation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When this young Prince from Charles his loynes deſcended,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then Rachels mourning for loſt iſſue, ended.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Charles Stevvarte.</l>
               <l>A true ſure caſtle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A true ſure Caſtle providence divine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hath given to Britaine ſince her civill warres.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princes deſcended from the regall line</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are ſorts 'gainſt forreigne foes, and homebred jarres.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Charles Stevvarte.</l>
               <l>Shal Vertues trace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your ſteps (if you your Parents paths regard)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall vertues trace: vertues ſhall you reward.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The happy expectation raiſed by the birth of the Duke of Yorke, hath beene attended by the following Anagrams.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Iacobus Steuartus regius Eboracensium Heros.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Svavi ego virtute crescens Muſis rosa habebor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold the roſe that (as the Muſes ſay)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſt ſweetly growes in vertue every day.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Iacobus Steuart.</l>
               <l>Tu ſatus Eboraci.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Planted at Yorke through honours princely due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where anciently the royall white roſe grew.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:8"/>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Iacobus Steuartus.</l>
               <l>Tuis ô carus, beatus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O deare, O bleſſed Babe, borne to encreaſe</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Iacobus Steuartius.</l>
               <l>Tuos carus beaviſti.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Parents hopes, your Countryes happineſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Iacobus Stevvartus Princeps.</l>
               <l>Tunè pius ac caſtus Puer Orbis?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mirrour of pious and chaſt moderation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To all the world in happy expectation!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Iacobus Stevvartius Heros.</l>
               <l>Herus eis vocabor, at Iuſtus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Follow your Grand-ſire (as your name doth bynde you)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So ſhall your followers a</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <l>Iames Stuart. A Iuſt Maſter.</l>
                     <l>Sylveſters Anagram.</l>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>iuſt maſter finde you.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Iames Stewart of Britayne.</l>
               <l>Streames of a witty braine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Iames Stewarde of Brittayne.</l>
               <l>Of rareſt maieſty and Bewtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Iames Stevvart.</l>
               <l>Aim's at vertues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee in the fountaines whence you ſprang, deſcry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That you ſhall flow with ſtreames of wit moſt cleare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That vertue, bewty, and rare maieſty</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall you endow, and to the World endeere.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The great hopes that Great Britaines Inhabitants have conceived of the Lady Mary their Princeſſe, and the great loue they beare her, are ſet forth in the following Anagrams.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramm.</head>
               <l>De Matia Stevvartia Caroli prole.</l>
               <l>Clara viris Dea, vita, amor et lepor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Men you'le prove a goddeſſe bright,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their life, their love, and their delight.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11016:8"/>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvartia Regis Proles.</l>
               <l>Grata viris Matris lepore ſuae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleaſing in ſhewing forth your mothers Grace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anagramma</hi> duplex.</head>
               <l>De Maria Stuartia.</l>
               <l>1. Ter viris adamata.</l>
               <l>2. Amata terris Diva.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thrice lov'd for princely worth in every place.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Maria Stevvartia.</l>
               <l>Vita aurea Matris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your mothers life, a childe whom Heav'n endeer's;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Borne to prolong the Parents golden years.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>De ter-foelicis et regalis tori prole, Maria Steuartia ac Borbonia.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Foelicitèr de alterâ orbis ſecuritate bonâ gloriari Maria potes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Well may you glory that you did ſupply</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The World with other good</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">for royall ſucceſſion.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecuritie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto the fayreſt Brittaine Lady, Mary Stevvard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagram.</head>
               <l>Art vertuously maintain'd by thy deareſt Father.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let golden vertues crowne your mayden dayes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in your nurture ſpred your Parents prayſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>To the Ladie Mary Stevvarde.</l>
               <l>Al doe admire at thy vertues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>A double Anagr.</head>
               <l>[Marie Stevvarde.]</l>
               <l>1. True as ever Maid.</l>
               <l>2. A sure true Maide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>To the Lady Mary Stewarde.</l>
               <l>Art eſteem'd a worthy Lady.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>A double Anagr.</head>
               <l>[Vnto the Ladie Marie Stevvard.]</l>
               <l>1. Art the vertuous<note n="*" place="margin">Diana.</note> Delian maide.</l>
               <l>2. Art the vertuous maiden Ladie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>You are in riſeing worth and vertues rare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like that chaſte Delian Mayd Diana fayre.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:9"/>
            <head>Anagrams upon all the Engliſh Monarches that have lived and dyed ſince the union of the royall roſes and houſes of Yorke and Lancaſter; from Henry the ſeventh ſurnamed Theodore alias Tider, the author of that happy union, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iames the firſt, the bleſſed vniter of the kingdomes of Great Britaine.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagr.</head>
               <l>Henricus ſeptimus Theodorus Monarcha.</l>
               <l>Tu roſis numen eras ac decor optimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>You were that power which did both roſes raiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adorning them with faire and peacefull dayes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Henricus ſeptimus Theodorus Monarcha Angliae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma duplex.</head>
               <l>1. Tu roſis decor, ac ope tuâ munimen Anglis eras.</l>
               <l>2. Tu notus unione rosis pacem declaras regiam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>To th'Engliſh Roſes which did long diſſent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You were a ſafegard and an ornament.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fame ſpread's your worth, whoſe wiſdome did connect</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Roſes, and a royall peace effect.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Henricus octavus Theodorus Monarcha Angliae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>En viramatus! O decor Anglis, ac novus Hector!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Loe he was Englands beautious love and praiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And like another Hector in his dayes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Edvardus VI. Tiderus Rex Anglicus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>En dulcis arvus Dei dextrâ riguus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Prince like ſome faire plot of pleaſant land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Was water'd euery jot with Gods right hand.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Maria Theodora olim Regina Anglorum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma</head>
               <l>Oh genti molli dura! An mot igero amata?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hard to the milde! Biller in indignation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To the obedient childe! Oh where's compaſſion?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma duplex.</head>
               <l>Eliſabetha Regina.</l>
               <l>1. An hera ſit Belgiae.</l>
               <l>2 Sitne Belgiae Ara?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>This royall Maid, in Belgia's great diſtreſſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Was her re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itſe, her ayde, her Governeſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eliſabetha Theodora Regina Angliae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Lactabaris Regina, Deo magno vltore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though foes aroſe, ſhe had a joyfull raigne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God did revenge her cauſe; their force reſtraine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Iacobus primus Stuartius, Angliae et</l>
               <l>Scotiae Monarcha pacificus, doctissimus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Anagramma.</head>
               <l>Rectiùs (ô!) doctus chartis, Legis pia meta,</l>
               <l>Norma fuit Musis, ac pacis vi, Hic, bonus Aſa!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Through learnings better helpes be ſought to hound</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strict Lawes within right limits. Him we found</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Rule vnto the Muſes, and inveſted</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With peace, like</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Land had reſt and he had no warre. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſa, when all Iudah reſted.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11016:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
